<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="cosmic_home_visibility_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2026 Playtron

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="home screen visibility protocol for layer surfaces">
    This protocol allows layer-shell clients to control their visibility
    based on whether the compositor is in "home" mode or not.
    
    Home mode represents the state where no regular toplevel windows are
    visible - similar to the iOS home screen. Layer surfaces can register
    as "home only" to be visible only in this state, or remain "always
    visible" (the default) like a top panel or dock.
    
    The compositor controls when home mode is active, typically:
    - Entering home mode when Super key is pressed (minimizes all windows)
    - Leaving home mode when a window is activated or restored
  </description>

  <interface name="zcosmic_home_visibility_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="manager for home visibility">
      This interface allows layer-shell clients to register for home
      visibility control and receive home state change events.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager">
        Destroy this manager object.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="get_home_visibility">
      <description summary="get home visibility controller for a layer surface">
        Create a home visibility controller for the given wl_surface.
        The surface must be a layer-shell surface (zwlr_layer_surface_v1).
        
        By default, layer surfaces are "always visible". Use the controller
        to set them as "home only" if they should only appear when the
        compositor is in home mode.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="zcosmic_home_visibility_v1"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
    </request>

    <event name="home_state">
      <description summary="home state changed">
        Sent when the compositor enters or leaves home mode. Also sent
        immediately after binding to provide the initial state.
        
        Clients can use this to adjust their UI, for example showing
        different content when at home vs when windows are visible.
      </description>
      <arg name="is_home" type="uint" summary="1 if at home, 0 if not"/>
    </event>
  </interface>

  <interface name="zcosmic_home_visibility_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="home visibility controller for a layer surface">
      This interface controls whether a layer surface is visible only
      when the compositor is in home mode, or always visible.
    </description>

    <enum name="visibility_mode">
      <description summary="visibility mode for the layer surface">
        Defines when the layer surface should be visible.
      </description>
      <entry name="always" value="0" summary="always visible (default)"/>
      <entry name="home_only" value="1" summary="visible only when at home"/>
      <entry name="hide_on_home" value="2" summary="hidden when at home (inverse of home_only)"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy this controller">
        Destroy this home visibility controller. The surface reverts
        to "always visible" behavior.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="set_visibility_mode">
      <description summary="set the visibility mode">
        Set when this layer surface should be visible.
        
        - always (0): Surface is always visible regardless of home state
        - home_only (1): Surface is only visible when compositor is in home mode
        - hide_on_home (2): Surface is hidden when in home mode (inverse fade)
        
        The default is "always" to maintain backwards compatibility with
        existing layer-shell clients.
      </description>
      <arg name="mode" type="uint" enum="visibility_mode"/>
    </request>
  </interface>
</protocol>
