<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="cosmic_layer_surface_dismiss_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2026 Playtron

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="dismiss notifications for layer surface popups">
    This protocol allows layer-shell clients to receive notifications when
    user interaction occurs outside their surfaces. This enables "close on
    click outside" behavior for popup menus without changing keyboard focus.

    Unlike xdg_popup which has built-in grab semantics, layer-shell surfaces
    need an external mechanism to detect outside interactions. This protocol
    provides that mechanism while:
    - Not changing keyboard focus (app-specific menus still work)
    - Not affecting the focused application state
    - Working with multiple related surfaces (e.g., panel bar + popup)

    Typical usage:
    1. Panel opens a popup layer surface
    2. Panel registers the popup for dismiss notifications
    3. User clicks on an application window
    4. Compositor sends dismiss_requested to the popup
    5. Panel closes the popup
  </description>

  <interface name="zcosmic_layer_surface_dismiss_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="manager for layer surface dismiss notifications">
      This interface allows layer-shell clients to register surfaces for
      dismiss notifications when interaction occurs outside them.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager">
        Destroy this manager object. Does not affect any dismiss
        controllers that were created.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="get_dismiss_controller">
      <description summary="get dismiss controller for a layer surface">
        Create a dismiss controller for the given wl_surface.
        The surface must be a layer-shell surface (zwlr_layer_surface_v1).
        
        Only one controller can exist per surface. Creating a second
        controller for the same surface is a protocol error.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="zcosmic_layer_surface_dismiss_v1"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
    </request>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="already_constructed" value="0"
             summary="the surface already has a dismiss controller"/>
      <entry name="invalid_surface" value="1"
             summary="the surface is not a layer-shell surface"/>
    </enum>
  </interface>

  <interface name="zcosmic_layer_surface_dismiss_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="dismiss controller for a layer surface">
      This interface controls dismiss notifications for a specific
      layer-shell surface. When armed, the compositor will send a
      dismiss_requested event when the user interacts with any surface
      outside the registered surface group.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the dismiss controller">
        Destroy this dismiss controller. The surface will no longer
        receive dismiss notifications.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="arm">
      <description summary="start listening for outside interactions">
        Arm the dismiss notification. After this call, the compositor
        will monitor for pointer button presses and touch events.
        
        When the user interacts with a surface that is NOT:
        - This surface
        - Any surface in the same dismiss group (see add_to_group)
        
        The compositor will send a dismiss_requested event.
        
        The dismiss notification automatically disarms after firing.
        Call arm() again to re-arm if needed.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="disarm">
      <description summary="stop listening for outside interactions">
        Disarm the dismiss notification. No dismiss_requested events
        will be sent until arm() is called again.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="add_to_group">
      <description summary="add another surface to the dismiss group">
        Add another surface to this controller's dismiss group.
        Interactions with surfaces in the same group will NOT trigger
        dismiss_requested events.
        
        This is useful when a panel has multiple related surfaces
        (e.g., the panel bar and its popup) and clicking the panel
        bar should not dismiss the popup.
        
        The added surface does not need its own dismiss controller.
      </description>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
    </request>

    <request name="remove_from_group">
      <description summary="remove a surface from the dismiss group">
        Remove a surface from this controller's dismiss group.
      </description>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
    </request>

    <event name="dismiss_requested">
      <description summary="interaction occurred outside the surface group">
        Sent when the user interacts (pointer button press, touch down)
        with a surface outside the dismiss group while armed.
        
        The client should typically close the popup in response.
        The dismiss notification is automatically disarmed after this
        event is sent.
      </description>
    </event>
  </interface>
</protocol>
