<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="layer_edge_resize">
  <copyright>
    Copyright 2026 Playtron

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be included in
    all copies or substantial portions of the Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND.
  </copyright>

  <interface name="layer_edge_resize_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="opt-in compositor-drawn edge resize for layer surfaces">
      Lets a layer-shell client opt a surface into a compositor-drawn,
      VSCode-style edge resize sash on its outer (non-anchored) edge. The
      compositor infers the resizable edge from the surface's anchor, draws a
      themed indicator on hover near that edge, shows an EW-resize cursor, and
      on press+drag shows a ghost that the surface springs to on release. The
      resize is fully compositor-driven; the client only opts in and supplies
      width bounds.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager">
        Destroying the manager does not affect already-created
        layer_edge_resize_v1 objects.
      </description>
    </request>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="already_exists" value="0"
        summary="an edge_resize object already exists for this surface"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="get_edge_resize">
      <description summary="enable edge resize for a layer surface">
        Create an edge-resize object for the given layer surface. Only one such
        object may exist per surface; a second request raises already_exists.
        The surface is expected to be a layer-shell surface anchored to a single
        vertical edge (left or right).
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="layer_edge_resize_v1"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"
        summary="the layer surface to make edge-resizable"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="layer_edge_resize_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="per-surface edge-resize handle">
      Carries the width bounds for one edge-resizable layer surface. Bounds are
      in logical pixels and take effect immediately (no commit required); they
      constrain the next drag. Defaults are compositor-defined until set.
    </description>

    <request name="set_min_width">
      <description summary="minimum surface width in logical px"/>
      <arg name="width" type="int" summary="minimum width, logical px"/>
    </request>

    <request name="set_max_width">
      <description summary="maximum surface width in logical px (0 = output width)"/>
      <arg name="width" type="int" summary="maximum width, logical px; 0 means full output width"/>
    </request>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="disable edge resize for this surface"/>
    </request>
  </interface>
</protocol>
