<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="layer_auto_hide">
  <copyright><![CDATA[
    Copyright © 2024 Playtron

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT.  IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  ]]></copyright>

  <description summary="compositor-driven auto-hide for layer surfaces">
    This protocol allows layer shell surfaces to register for compositor-driven
    auto-hide behavior. When any toplevel window on the same output is maximized
    or fullscreen, the compositor animates registered surfaces off the specified
    screen edge. The compositor handles all animation and hover detection
    internally, providing smooth 60fps transitions synchronized with the render
    loop.
  </description>

  <interface name="layer_auto_hide_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="auto-hide manager for layer surfaces">
      Manager for creating auto-hide objects for layer shell surfaces.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager">
        Informs the server that the client will no longer use this global.
        Existing auto-hide objects remain valid until destroyed.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="get_auto_hide">
      <description summary="create auto-hide object for a surface">
        Create an auto-hide controller for the given wl_surface.

        If the given wl_surface already has a layer_auto_hide_v1 object
        associated, the already_exists protocol error is raised.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="layer_auto_hide_v1"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
    </request>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="already_exists" value="0"
        summary="surface already has an auto-hide object"/>
    </enum>
  </interface>

  <interface name="layer_auto_hide_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="auto-hide controller for a surface">
      Controls compositor-driven auto-hide for a layer shell surface.

      When auto-hide is active, the compositor:
      - Hides the surface (slides it off-screen) when any toplevel on the
        same output is maximized or fullscreen
      - Shows the surface when the pointer enters the edge zone
      - Hides the surface again when the pointer leaves (while maximized
        windows exist)
      - Shows the surface when no maximized/fullscreen windows remain

      All animations run at compositor frame rate for smooth 60fps transitions.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the auto-hide object">
        Disables auto-hide and destroys this object. If the surface is
        currently hidden, it will be shown immediately.
      </description>
    </request>

    <enum name="edge">
      <description summary="screen edge for auto-hide">
        Specifies which output edge the surface slides toward when hidden.
      </description>
      <entry name="bottom" value="0" summary="slide off the bottom edge"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="set_auto_hide">
      <description summary="enable auto-hide">
        Enable compositor-driven auto-hide for this surface. The surface will
        slide off the specified edge when maximized/fullscreen windows are
        present on the same output.

        The edge_zone parameter specifies how many pixels at the screen edge
        will trigger hover-to-show when the surface is hidden. This should
        be a small value (e.g. 2-8 pixels).

        Calling this again replaces the previous configuration.
      </description>
      <arg name="edge" type="uint" enum="edge"
        summary="which edge to slide off"/>
      <arg name="edge_zone" type="uint"
        summary="hover detection zone in pixels"/>
    </request>

    <request name="unset_auto_hide">
      <description summary="disable auto-hide">
        Disables auto-hide. If the surface is currently hidden, it will be
        shown immediately.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="visibility_changed">
      <description summary="visibility state changed">
        Sent by the compositor when the auto-hide visibility state changes.
        The client can use this to adjust behavior (e.g. skip expensive
        rendering when hidden, update input regions).

        Only sent while auto-hide is active.
      </description>
      <arg name="visible" type="uint"
        summary="1 if fully visible, 0 if fully hidden"/>
    </event>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="surface_destroyed" value="0"
        summary="the associated surface has been destroyed"/>
    </enum>
  </interface>
</protocol>
