<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="cosmic_layer_surface_visibility_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2026 Playtron

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="client-controlled visibility for layer surfaces">
    This protocol allows layer-shell clients to hide and show their surfaces
    without destroying them. This is useful for popup menus and panels that
    need instant visibility toggling without the overhead of surface
    creation/destruction.
    
    Hidden surfaces:
    - Are not rendered or composited (saves GPU resources)
    - Do not receive input events
    - Maintain their layer shell configuration (anchor, size, etc.)
    - Can be shown instantly without Wayland roundtrip overhead
  </description>

  <interface name="zcosmic_layer_surface_visibility_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="manager for layer surface visibility">
      This interface allows layer-shell clients to control the visibility
      of their surfaces.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager">
        Destroy this manager object. Does not affect any visibility
        controllers that were created.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="get_visibility_controller">
      <description summary="get visibility controller for a layer surface">
        Create a visibility controller for the given wl_surface.
        The surface must be a layer-shell surface (zwlr_layer_surface_v1).
        
        Only one controller can exist per surface. Creating a second
        controller for the same surface is a protocol error.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="zcosmic_layer_surface_visibility_v1"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="zcosmic_layer_surface_visibility_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="visibility controller for a layer surface">
      This interface controls whether a layer surface is visible or hidden.
      
      By default, surfaces are visible. Use set_hidden to hide the surface
      and set_visible to show it again.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy this controller">
        Destroy this visibility controller. The surface becomes visible
        if it was hidden.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="set_hidden">
      <description summary="hide the surface">
        Hide this layer surface. The surface will not be rendered or
        receive input events until set_visible is called.
        
        The surface maintains its configuration and can be shown instantly.
        This is more efficient than destroying and recreating the surface.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="set_visible">
      <description summary="show the surface">
        Show this layer surface if it was previously hidden.
        
        The surface will be rendered and can receive input events again.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="visibility_changed">
      <description summary="visibility state changed">
        Sent when the visibility state changes, either due to a client
        request or compositor action. Also sent immediately after the
        controller is created to provide the initial state.
      </description>
      <arg name="visible" type="uint" summary="1 if visible, 0 if hidden"/>
    </event>
  </interface>
</protocol>
