<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="layer_usable_area">
  <copyright><![CDATA[
    Copyright © 2026 Playtron

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT.  IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  ]]></copyright>

  <description summary="report the usable (non-exclusive) area of a surface's output">
    This protocol lets a layer shell surface learn the usable area of the
    output it is shown on: the output's logical geometry minus every exclusive
    zone reserved by other layer surfaces (panels, docks, bars).

    A centered or anchored overlay (launcher, switcher, system dialog) cannot
    compute this itself — only the compositor knows the exclusive zones of the
    other surfaces, and a non-overlapping surface receives nothing from the
    overlap-notify protocol. With the usable area in hand the client can center
    its content in the space actually free of panels rather than the full
    output, on the correct per-output basis and updated live as panels appear,
    disappear, resize, or toggle auto-hide.

    Warning! The protocol described in this file is currently in the testing
    phase. Backward compatible changes may be added together with the
    corresponding interface version bump. Backward incompatible changes can
    only be done by creating a new major version of the extension.
  </description>

  <interface name="layer_usable_area_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="usable area manager for layer surfaces">
      Manager for creating usable-area feedback objects for layer shell
      surfaces.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager">
        Informs the server that the client will no longer use this global.
        Existing usable-area objects remain valid until destroyed.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="get_usable_area">
      <description summary="get usable-area feedback for a surface">
        Create a usable-area feedback object for the given wl_surface, which
        must be a layer shell surface.

        If the given wl_surface already has a layer_usable_area_v1 object
        associated, the already_exists protocol error is raised.

        The compositor sends an initial usable_area event as soon as the
        surface's output is known, and again whenever the usable area of that
        output changes.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="layer_usable_area_v1"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
    </request>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="already_exists" value="0"
        summary="surface already has a usable-area object"/>
    </enum>
  </interface>

  <interface name="layer_usable_area_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="usable-area feedback for a surface">
      Reports the usable (non-exclusive) area of the output the associated
      surface is currently shown on. The rectangle is expressed in the
      output's logical coordinate space (the same space as xdg-output logical
      geometry), so the location is relative to the output's top-left corner.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the usable-area object">
        Informs the compositor that the client is no longer interested in
        usable-area updates for the surface.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="usable_area">
      <description summary="usable area changed">
        Sent by the compositor with the current usable area of the output the
        surface is shown on, in that output's logical coordinates. Sent once
        when the object is created (once the output is known) and again
        whenever the value changes (a panel maps, unmaps, resizes, or its
        exclusive zone changes, or the output is reconfigured).
      </description>
      <arg name="x" type="int" summary="usable area left, output-logical px"/>
      <arg name="y" type="int" summary="usable area top, output-logical px"/>
      <arg name="width" type="int" summary="usable area width, logical px"/>
      <arg name="height" type="int" summary="usable area height, logical px"/>
    </event>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="surface_destroyed" value="0"
        summary="the associated surface has been destroyed"/>
    </enum>
  </interface>
</protocol>
