<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="layer_surface_placement">
  <copyright><![CDATA[
    Copyright © 2026 Playtron

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT.  IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  ]]></copyright>

  <description summary="compositor-side placement of a layer surface within the usable area">
    This protocol lets a layer shell surface ask the compositor to position it
    within the output's usable (non-exclusive) area — the output's logical
    geometry minus every exclusive zone reserved by other layer surfaces
    (panels, docks, bars) — instead of computing and applying margins itself.

    A centered or fractionally-placed overlay (launcher, switcher, system
    dialog) otherwise has to learn the usable area, compute a margin, and apply
    it only after the surface is already mapped. The usable area is reported a
    frame or more after map (and again whenever the surface lands on a new
    output), so the surface visibly jumps from its first position to the
    corrected one. By describing the desired placement declaratively, the client
    lets the compositor position the surface at map time and keep it positioned
    across relayouts (panels appearing, resizing, or the surface moving to
    another output) with no client round-trip and no jump.

    The placement only takes effect while the surface is not anchored on the
    axis it controls and reserves no exclusive zone; an anchored or exclusive
    surface is positioned by the standard layer-shell rules instead. Horizontal
    placement is left to the standard layer-shell rules — a surface that is not
    anchored horizontally is centered within the usable area.

    This protocol is companion to layer_usable_area, which reports the usable
    area to clients that position themselves; here the compositor does the
    positioning. A client never needs both for the same surface.

    Warning! The protocol described in this file is currently in the testing
    phase. Backward compatible changes may be added together with the
    corresponding interface version bump. Backward incompatible changes can
    only be done by creating a new major version of the extension.
  </description>

  <interface name="layer_surface_placement_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="placement manager for layer surfaces">
      Manager for creating placement objects for layer shell surfaces.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager">
        Informs the server that the client will no longer use this global.
        Existing placement objects remain valid until destroyed.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="get_layer_surface_placement">
      <description summary="get a placement object for a surface">
        Create a placement object for the given wl_surface, which must be a
        layer shell surface.

        If the given wl_surface already has a layer_surface_placement_v1 object
        associated, the already_exists protocol error is raised.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="layer_surface_placement_v1"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
    </request>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="already_exists" value="0"
        summary="surface already has a placement object"/>
    </enum>
  </interface>

  <interface name="layer_surface_placement_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="placement control for a layer surface">
      Controls how the compositor positions the associated layer surface within
      its output's usable (non-exclusive) area.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the placement object">
        Clears any compositor-side placement and reverts the surface to standard
        layer-shell positioning.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="set_vertical_placement">
      <description summary="place the surface vertically within the usable area">
        Position the surface's top edge at

          usable_top + round(fraction * usable_height) + offset

        clamped so the top edge is at least min_margin below the usable area's
        top edge, where usable_top/usable_height are that of the output the
        surface is shown on, in logical pixels.

        The placement takes effect at the next layout pass and persists — it is
        re-applied on every relayout (a panel maps, unmaps, resizes, or the
        surface moves to another output) — until changed by another
        set_vertical_placement, cleared by unset_vertical_placement, or the
        object is destroyed.

        This only takes effect while the surface is not anchored vertically
        (neither top nor bottom) and reserves no exclusive zone; otherwise the
        standard layer-shell positioning applies.

        fraction is a wl_fixed value, normally in the range [0.0, 1.0]. offset
        and min_margin are signed/unsigned logical pixels respectively.
      </description>
      <arg name="fraction" type="fixed"
        summary="fraction of usable-area height for the surface's top edge"/>
      <arg name="offset" type="int"
        summary="additional vertical offset, logical px (signed)"/>
      <arg name="min_margin" type="int"
        summary="minimum gap from the usable-area top, logical px"/>
    </request>

    <request name="unset_vertical_placement">
      <description summary="clear compositor-side vertical placement">
        Revert the surface to standard layer-shell vertical positioning: anchor
        plus margin, or — for a surface not anchored vertically — vertical
        centering within the usable area.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="set_max_height">
      <description summary="cap the surface height to a fraction of the usable area">
        Clamp the surface's height to `max(round(fraction * usable_height),
        min_height)` logical pixels, where usable_height is that of the output
        the surface is shown on. This lets the client commit its full content
        height and have the compositor cap it to a fraction of the usable area
        (e.g. a grid that scrolls past 76% of the available height), without the
        client recomputing the cap from a usable-area value that is stale right
        after the surface appears on a new output.

        Like set_vertical_placement, this is re-applied on every relayout and
        persists until changed by another set_max_height, cleared by
        unset_max_height, or the object is destroyed. It composes with
        set_vertical_placement and with vertical centering (the cap is applied
        before the surface is positioned).

        fraction is a wl_fixed value, normally in the range [0.0, 1.0].
        min_height is a floor (in logical px) for the resolved cap so a small
        output can't shrink the surface below a usable minimum; pass 0 for none.
      </description>
      <arg name="fraction" type="fixed"
        summary="fraction of usable-area height to cap the surface to"/>
      <arg name="min_height" type="int"
        summary="floor for the resolved cap, logical px"/>
    </request>

    <request name="unset_max_height">
      <description summary="clear the compositor-side height cap">
        Remove any height cap set by set_max_height; the surface is sized by the
        standard layer-shell rules (its requested size, clamped to the zone).
      </description>
    </request>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="surface_destroyed" value="0"
        summary="the associated surface has been destroyed"/>
    </enum>
  </interface>
</protocol>
