<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="zcosmic_tooltip_v1">
  <copyright><![CDATA[
    Copyright © 2025 Playtron

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT.  IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  ]]></copyright>

  <description summary="compositor-driven pointer-following tooltips">
    This protocol allows clients to create tooltip surfaces that the compositor
    positions relative to the pointer cursor automatically. Instead of the
    client receiving pointer motion events and issuing xdg_popup.reposition()
    round-trips, the compositor tracks the pointer position internally and
    repositions the tooltip surface each frame, eliminating latency.

    The client provides a tooltip surface and a parent surface. While the
    pointer is over the parent surface, the compositor positions the tooltip
    at pointer_position + offset. The client configures the offset and anchor
    via requests on the tooltip object.
  </description>

  <interface name="zcosmic_tooltip_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="tooltip manager">
      Manager for creating compositor-driven tooltip objects.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager">
        Informs the server that the client will no longer use this global.
        Existing tooltip objects remain valid until destroyed.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="get_tooltip">
      <description summary="create a tooltip object">
        Create a compositor-driven tooltip controller for the given surface.

        The tooltip_surface is the wl_surface that will be displayed as the
        tooltip. The parent_surface is the wl_surface that the tooltip is
        associated with — the compositor will position the tooltip relative
        to the pointer only while the pointer is over the parent surface.

        If the given tooltip_surface already has a zcosmic_tooltip_v1 object
        associated, the already_exists protocol error is raised.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="zcosmic_tooltip_v1"/>
      <arg name="tooltip_surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
      <arg name="parent_surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
    </request>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="already_exists" value="0"
        summary="tooltip_surface already has a tooltip object"/>
    </enum>
  </interface>

  <interface name="zcosmic_tooltip_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="compositor-driven tooltip">
      Controls a compositor-driven tooltip surface. The compositor positions
      the tooltip surface at the pointer position plus the configured offset,
      constrained to the output boundaries.

      The tooltip is shown when the pointer enters the parent surface and
      hidden when the pointer leaves. The client must still commit content
      to the tooltip surface — the compositor only handles positioning.

      All position values are in surface-local coordinates of the parent.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the tooltip object">
        Destroys the tooltip controller. The tooltip surface will be hidden
        immediately.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="set_offset">
      <description summary="set tooltip offset from pointer">
        Set the offset in logical pixels from the pointer position to the
        tooltip surface's top-left corner. This is double-buffered and
        applied on the next wl_surface.commit of the tooltip surface.

        Default offset is (0, 0).
      </description>
      <arg name="x" type="int" summary="horizontal offset in logical pixels"/>
      <arg name="y" type="int" summary="vertical offset in logical pixels"/>
    </request>

    <request name="set_anchor">
      <description summary="set tooltip anchor point">
        Set which corner of the tooltip surface is anchored to the pointer
        position (plus offset). This is double-buffered and applied on the
        next wl_surface.commit of the tooltip surface.

        Default anchor is top_left.
      </description>
      <arg name="anchor" type="uint" enum="anchor" summary="anchor point"/>
    </request>

    <request name="set_show_delay">
      <description summary="set delay before showing the tooltip">
        Set the delay in milliseconds before the tooltip is shown after the
        pointer enters the parent surface. If set to 0 (the default), the
        tooltip is shown immediately when the pointer enters the parent.

        When a non-zero delay is set, the tooltip remains hidden until the
        pointer has been over the parent surface continuously for the
        specified duration. If the pointer leaves the parent surface before
        the delay expires, the timer resets.

        When a delay is set, the tooltip is positioned at the pointer
        location at the moment the delay expires. The tooltip stays at
        that fixed position (it does not follow the pointer) until it is
        hidden when the pointer leaves the parent surface.

        This is double-buffered and applied on the next wl_surface.commit
        of the tooltip surface.
      </description>
      <arg name="milliseconds" type="uint" summary="delay in milliseconds (0 = immediate)"/>
    </request>

    <enum name="anchor">
      <description summary="tooltip anchor point">
        Which corner of the tooltip is placed at pointer + offset.
      </description>
      <entry name="top_left" value="0" summary="top-left corner"/>
      <entry name="top_right" value="1" summary="top-right corner"/>
      <entry name="bottom_left" value="2" summary="bottom-left corner"/>
      <entry name="bottom_right" value="3" summary="bottom-right corner"/>
    </enum>

    <event name="reposition">
      <description summary="tooltip was repositioned">
        Sent by the compositor when the tooltip surface has been repositioned.
        The x and y values are the position in the parent surface's coordinate
        space. This event is sent each time the compositor updates the tooltip
        position (i.e. on each pointer motion frame).

        The client may use this for informational purposes but does not need
        to respond — the compositor handles all positioning.
      </description>
      <arg name="x" type="int" summary="x position relative to parent"/>
      <arg name="y" type="int" summary="y position relative to parent"/>
    </event>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="surface_destroyed" value="0"
        summary="the associated surface has been destroyed"/>
    </enum>
  </interface>
</protocol>
